{"tossups": [{"question": "One side at this battle failed to penetrate earthworks along the Rodriguez Canal, suffering over two thousand casualties to the Americans\u2019 seventy-one. British general Edward Pakenham was killed while Jean Lafitte assisted the victors in this battle, fought two weeks after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent that ended the War of 1812. For ten points, name this military victory for Andrew Jackson, which took place outside a large city in Louisiana.", "answer": "Battle of<b> New Orleans</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Though Percival Lowell initially predicted this body\u2019s existence, Clyde Tombaugh discovered it using an astrograph. Photographs of this body from 12,500 kilometers were taken by the New Horizons space probe in July 2015. For ten points, name this body that was the smallest planet in our solar system prior to its controversial reclassification as a dwarf planet in 2006.", "answer": "<b> Pluto</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "This man was forced to duel Humphrey Marshall after proposing a law that banned British cloth in favor of homespun cloth. This man argued with Andrew Jackson over the funding of the Maysville Road as part of the American System. They feuded again when this Speaker of the House awarded the Election of 1824 to John Quincy Adams as part of a \u201ccorrupt bargain.\u201d For ten points, name this Kentucky senator, known as the \u201cGreat Compromiser.\u201d", "answer": "Henry<b> Clay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Arrivals at this place were asked a series of questions, controversially including the amount of money they carried, and the National Origins Act of 1924 imposed race-based quotas on the operations of this place. By the time this place closed in 1954, over 12 million people had passed through it. For ten points, identify this New York island which during the first half of the 20th century was the U.S.\u2019s busiest immigrant inspection port.", "answer": "<b> Ellis Island</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A Velazquez painting of this figure was attacked by suffragette Mary Richardson. A faceless depiction of this figure was discovered in 1908 by Joseph Szombathy in the village of Willendorf. In another painting, this figure is blown to shore by Zephyrus and stands on a giant shell. An armless statue discovered on the island of Milos depicts, for ten points, what goddess whose birth is depicted in a painting by Sandro Botticelli?", "answer": "<b> Venus</b> (accept<b> Aphrodite</b>; accept<b> Venus</b> of Willendorf, Rokeby<b> Venus</b>,<b> Venus</b> de Milo, or Birth of<b> Venus</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s navy fought off one attack by using fireships to thwart enemies at the battle of Gravelines [grav-LEEN]. One of this ruler\u2019s admirals launched a daring raid on Cadiz, boasting he had \u201csinged the beard\u201d of a rival king. This patron of Francis Drake gave the Tilbury speech, where this ruler declared she had the \u201cheart and stomach of a king\u201d in the face of invasion from the Spanish Armada. For ten points, name this daughter of Henry VIII, the \u201cvirgin queen\u201d of England.", "answer": "<b> Elizabeth I</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Girolamo Frescobaldi and Jean Lully Batiste were composers from the early part of this period. This period of music was significant for ushering in the transition from modal to tonal styles, and music from this period tended to be dense and complex, forming a polyphony of voices through arrangements such as the fugue. For ten points, identify this period of music named after the Portuguese word for \u201cmisshapen pearl,\u201d lasting from roughly 1600-1750 and including notable composers such as Bach and Handel.", "answer": "<b> Baroque</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man unsuccessfully conspired to get Thomas Pinckney elected president in 1796. This man was married to Eliza Schuyler [SKY-lur], but had an affair with Maria Reynolds. This man who established the U.S. Mint, and was also the primary author of the Federalist Papers, suggested a controversial tax on a particular alcoholic beverage while a member of George Washington\u2019s cabinet. For ten points, name this first Secretary of the Treasury, depicted on the U.S. $10 bill.", "answer": "Alexander<b> Hamilton</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The world\u2019s tallest statue of a woman commemorates this battle and is known as \u201cThe Motherland Calls.\u201d Soldiers stationed at Kalach-on-the-Don were encircled as part of this battle\u2019s Operation Uranus. A speech by Adolf Hitler named after this battle ends with him exclaiming \u201cI do not want a second Verdun there!\u201d An attempt to provide supplies to one side during Operation Winter Storm was thwarted by terrible weather at this 1942-43 battle. Over 1.7 million casualties occurred at, for ten points, what massive World War Two battle, where Germany surrendered to the Soviet Union?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Stalingrad</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The original land that made up this city during colonial times was bought by Jacob Van Curler and was used to establish Fort Hoop. This city derived its name from the English home town of Samuel Stone who brought settlers to this location from what is now Cambridge, Massachusetts. A treaty between New Netherland and the residents of this city in New England established a boundary along its colony\u2019s namesake river. A state quarter depicts a tree in this city where residents secretly hid a colonial charter. Located near New Haven, for ten points, name this capital of Connecticut.", "answer": "<b> Hartford</b>, Connecticut", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This vessel\u2019s remains are located at the Newport News Mariners Museum. The namesake of a type of warship with revolving gun turrets, this vessel was designed by John Ericcson, built in Brooklyn, and mocked as a \u201ccheesebox on a raft.\u201d This warship\u2019s arrival saved the USS<em> Minnesota</em>, and Lt. John Worden commanded it during its best known action at Hampton Roads, in which it faced a converted wooden craft formerly known as the<em> Merrimack</em>. For ten points, name this Civil War ironclad warship that fought for the Union against the CSS<em> Virginia</em>.", "answer": "USS<b> Monitor</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Carillon at this site was created by Coca-Cola for the 1964 World\u2019s Fair. The largest bas-relief sculpture in the world can be found at this site. A 2013 bell-ringing was held here during the fiftieth anniversary of Martin Luther King\u2019s \u201cI Have a Dream Speech\u201d in which King said \u201cLet Freedom Ring from [this site] of Georgia.\u201d After the release of<em> Birth of a Nation</em>, this monument became the site of the founding of the second Ku Klux Klan. Made of quartz monzonite, this monument contains depictions of Jefferson Davis and Robert E. Lee. For ten points, name this Confederate equivalent of Mount Rushmore.", "answer": "<b> Stone Mountain</b> Park", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "During the Boer War, this man served as a journalist and escaped from prison after being captured by Boer troops. In one speech, this man urged his countrymen to fight on the beaches and landing areas and never give up. This man claimed that he had nothing to offer but \u201cblood, toil, sweat, and tears.\u201dAfter the resignation of Neville Chamberlain, this man rose to his highest position of Prime Minister and led the U.K.\u2019s staunch resistance to Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this influential British leader.", "answer": "Winston<b> Churchill</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Its name is taken from the German word for \u201cLightning.\u201d", "answer": "The<b> Blitz</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The commercials during Super Bowl XXXIV [34] were named after this period. Steve Case and Ted Leonsis led one organization that declined but survived during this period. Mark Cuban made his fortune during this era, which was followed by collapses from Egghead Software, eToys, and Yahoo!. For ten points, name this venture capital-fueled bubble in the late-90s and early-2000s whose name derives from its hype of Internet-based companies.", "answer": "<b> Dot-com</b> bubble or boom (prompt on answers relating to 90s or 00s, accept<b> Tech</b> bubble or <b>Internet</b> bubble before it is mentioned))", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Perhaps the first person to serve in this role in the U.S. was former journalist Judson Welliver during the administrations of Harding and Coolidge. Much of</b><em><b> Profiles in Courage </b></em><b>was co-written by another person with this role named Ted Sorenson. While holding this role during Nixon\u2019s administration, (+) William Safire created the term \u201cnattering nabobs of negativism.\u201d Another person in this role, Peggy Noonan, coined the phrases \u201ca kinder, gentler nation\u201d and \u201cRead my (*)</b> lips: no new taxes.\u201d For ten points, name this profession of those who write inaugural comments and presidential State of the Union comments.", "answer": "Presidential<b> Speechwriter</b>s (accept equivalents)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One of these two countries refused to use force to put down the revolt of Colonel Ahmed Urabi, prompting the other to intervene militarily. Another incident between these two countries featured a territorial dispute in Sudan and ended with a troop standoff in (+) Fashoda. These two countries later worked with David Ben-Gurion in Operation Musketeer, deploying paratroopers to thwart Gamel Abdel Nasser\u2019s (*)</b> nationalization of a waterway. For ten points, name these two European powers that joined forces in the Suez Crisis.", "answer": "<b> United Kingdom</b> (accept UK, Britain, or England) and<b> France</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Nicolay de Caveri created one of these items based on another that a fellow countryman smuggled out of Portugal. Fifty-three of these were collected by Abraham Ortelius to create the</b><em><b> Theatrum Orbis Terrarum</b></em><b>. The preservation of (+) angles in a 1569 object of this type resulted in several key distortions. Martin Waldeseemuller\u2019s</b><em><b> Universalis Cosmographia</b></em><b> was an object of this type in which the name (*) </b> Amerigo Vespucci was used to identify certain new landmasses. The Mercator Projection is an example of, for ten points, what cartographic objects?", "answer": "<b> Map</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This program was named by Abe Silverstein and was defended in a speech that stated things like it are done \u201cnot because they are easy, but because they are hard.\u201d This program</b> <b>received a major setback in 1967 after (+)</b> <b>Ed White, Roger Chaffee, and Gus Grissom</b> <b>were killed in an accident during a test. After the eleventh mission of this program landed in the Sea of (*)</b> Tranquility, Neil Armstrong described his first step on the moon as \u201cone small step for man, one giant leap for mankind.\u201d For ten points, name this NASA manned space program that took men to the moon.", "answer": "<b> Apollo</b> program (prompt on \u201cmoon landing\u201d or equivalents prior to being mentioned) Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Max Eastman translated a three-volume history written by this man as well as a work in which this man claims that one leader is engaging in ineffective \u201czigzags\u201d in economic policy. That work by this man accuses a rival of engaging in \u201cBonapartism\u201d and is titled</b> <b>(+)</b> <em><b>The Revolution Betrayed</b></em><b>. In one essay, this man claims that \u201cthe task of arming the</b> <b>revolution falls with all its weight upon the proletariat,\u201d which is in reference to his desire to maintain the (*)</b> Red Army that he created. For ten points, name this Leftist Russian revolutionary whose assassination was ordered by Stalin.", "answer": "Leon<b> Trotsky</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In a famous confrontation with Valerian Zorin, this man said, \u201cI do not have your talent for obfuscation\u201d and that this man would potentially wait for a \u201cyes or no\u201d answer \u201cuntil</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>hell freezes over.\u201d This man was a member of a noted family including his father, the</b> <b>U.S. Vice President under Grover Cleveland. In 1949, this man succeeded Dwight Green as governor of Illinois before running in (*) </b> two presidential elections as the Democratic nominee, losing both times to a World War Two five-star general. For ten points, name this politician who lost those elections to Dwight Eisenhower.", "answer": "Adlai E(wing)<b> Stevenson II</b> ", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This location was purchased in 1901 by William and Annie Rogers duPont, whose daughter Marion founded an annual horse race held at this location. A slave born in this location attempted to engineer the largest slave escape in history in the (+)</b><em><b> Pearl </b></em><b>incident and wrote the first White House memoir. This birthplace of Paul Jennings was sold to Henry W. Moncure by the wife of the (*)</b> fourth American president. For ten points, name this estate near Orange, Virginia, that James Madison named after a French resort city on the Mediterranean.", "answer": "<b> Montpelier</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "By what colorful name is Teach better known?", "answer": "<b> Blackbeard</b> Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}